Public Health and Professional Degree Programs Records UA187
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Public Health and Professional Degree Programs Records
1990 -- 2011
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Dean for Public Heath and Professional Degree Programs
Public Health and Professional Degree Programs
UA187
22.8 Linear Feet 21 boxes
This collection contains records created by the Public Health and Professional Degree Program.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection contains some restricted material. Restrictions related to specific material are listed in the detailed contents list.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred by Janice Gilkes, the Director of Enrollment Services in Public Health and Professional Degree Programs at Tufts University School of Medicine, accession UA-2017-001.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into five series: Steering committee minutes; Academic affairs committee minutes; Accreditation files; Grade sheets; and 2016 accessions.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains records created by the Public Health and Professional Degree Program, particularly committee minutes, accreditation files, grade sheets, and student files from programs including the MD/MPH, the MPH (including MS/MPH, JD/MPH, BA/MPH), the HCOM, and Pain, Research Education and Policy.
Biographical / Historical
The Public Health and Professional Degree Programs (PHPD) was established in 1996, when the success of a combined Master in Medicine/Master of Public Health program at Tufts prompted the School of Medicine, in partnership with the faculty of Arts and Sciences and the School of Nutrition Science and Policy, to develop a freestanding interdisciplinary Master of Public Health. Originally called the Graduate Programs in Public Health (GPPH), around 2006 the program's name changed to the Public Health and Professional Degree Programs. The Public Health and Professional Degree Programs now provides oversight, administration, and student services for all master's degree programs offered by the medical school. Approved in 1985 by the Tufts University Board of Trustees, the MD/MPH is one of fifteen degree or joint degree programs offered by the medical school. The MD/MPH was the first program in the country to allow both degrees to be earned in four years. The first students enrolled in 1986. The combined program was designed to fill a growing need for physicians with advanced understanding of health promotion, disease prevention, epidemiology, the environment, health planning and global health problems. A combined DVM/MPH program, modeled after the successful MD/MPH program, was approved by the university to begin admitting students in 1994.
The combined MD/MPH was originally located administratively in the Department of Community Health, but with the advent of the newly established stand-alone MPH program in 1996, was situated in a reconfigured Department of Family Medicine and Community Health, which fell under the aegis of the Graduate Programs in Public Health along with the Doctor of Veterinary Medicine/Master of Public Health, Master of Public Health, and Master of Science in Health Communications (approved in 1994). This organizational move was intended to foster integration of the programs. The program was located on the first floor of the Medical and Veterinary building (now the Biomedical Research and Public Health Building). The new environment provided an interdisciplinary setting for the educational programs, providing students with access to varied areas of expertise and a public health setting. The programs also drew on multidisciplinary faculty resources from various schools at Tufts, other universities in the Boston area, and public and private agencies.
The commitment to interdisciplinary integration is reflected in the various degree programs as of 2017: the Physician Assistant/Master of Public Health, Master of Science in Nutrition/ Master of Public Health, Juris Doctor/Master of Public Health, Master in Medicine/Master of Business Administration, Bachelors/Master of Public Health, Master of Science in Biomedical Science/ Master of Public Health, Doctor of Medicine in Dentistry/ Master in Public Health, Master of Arts in Urban and Environmental Planning/ Master in Public Health, Doctorate of Public Health, Master of Science in Pharmacology and Drug Development, and Master of Science in Pain Research, Education, and Policy, approved in 1999.
The governance of the GPPH initially included two distinct structures: the combined program was integrated into the medical or veterinary curriculum planning and approval processes while the MPH operated under a more flexible structure. The combined program was served by two standing committees: the Policy Advisory Group (PAG) and the Admissions Committee. A single academic affairs/admissions committee served as a standing committee for the MPH program. By 2001, GHHP governance was divided into several committees: academic affairs, admissions and recruitment, student life committee, student ethics and grievance committee, external advisory board, and steering committee. All committees reported to the Director of the GPPH. The initial curriculum for the MPH program offered 36-credit, 48-credit and 60-credit programs of study. The curriculum was presented in a traditional academic calendar and emphasized evening courses to attract working students. Students in the 36 and 48 credit MPH programs could select from four concentrations: epidemiology and biostatistics, nutrition, environmental health, and health service management and policy. The MPH program now offers an additional concentration in Global Health.
Curriculum and Instruction -- Academic Departments and Programs
- Steering Committee minutes, 1994 -- 2009; UA187.001; 1.2 Linear Feet
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains records related to the Professional Degree Programs steering committee.
  Arrangement
  This series is by topic.
  Conditions Governing Access
  20 years from date of creation.
  - GPPH Steering Committee Minutes, 1998 -- 1999; UA187.001.001.00001 (Box UA187 Shared 1)
  - GPPH Steering Committee Minutes, 1999 -- 2000; UA187.001.001.00002 (Box UA187 Shared 1)
  - GPPH Steering Committee Minutes, 2000 -- 2001; UA187.001.001.00003 (Box UA187 Shared 1)
  - GPPH Steering Committee Minutes, 2001 -- 2002; UA187.001.001.00004 (Box UA187 Shared 1)
  - GPPH Steering Committee Minutes, 2002 -- 2003; UA187.001.001.00005 (Box UA187 Shared 1)
  - GPPH Steering Committee Minutes, 2003 -- 2004; UA187.001.001.00006 (Box UA187 Shared 1)
  - GPPH Steering Committee Minutes, 2004 -- 2005; UA187.001.001.00007 (Box UA187 Shared 1)
  - GPPH Steering Committee Minutes, 2005 -- 2006; UA187.001.001.00008 (Box UA187 Shared 1)
  - Policy Advising Group, 1994 -- 1997; UA187.001.001.00009 (Box UA187 Shared 1)
  - GPPH Promotions Sub-Committee Minutes, 1999 -- 2002; UA187.001.001.00010 (Box UA187 Shared 1)
  - GPPH External Advisory Board, 1998 -- 1999; UA187.001.001.00011 (Box UA187 Shared 1)
  - MD/MBA Program Minutes, 1999 -- 2001; UA187.001.001.00012 (Box UA187 Shared 1)
  - MD/MBA Steering Committee Minutes, 2002 -- 2003; UA187.001.001.00013 (Box UA187 Shared 1)
  - MD/MBA Steering Committee Minutes, 2003 -- 2004; UA187.001.001.00014 (Box UA187 Shared 1)
  - MD/MBA Steering Committee Minutes, 2004 -- 2005; UA187.001.001.00015 (Box UA187 Shared 1)
  - CMBA Steering Committee Meetings, 2005 -- 2006; UA187.001.001.00016 (Box UA187 Shared 1)
  - CMBA Steering Committee Meetings, 2006 -- 2007; UA187.001.001.00017 (Box UA187 Shared 1)
  - MPH/HCOM Steering Committee Meetings, 2006 -- 2007; UA187.001.001.00018 (Box UA187 Shared 1)
  - MPH/HCOM Sub-Committee, 2009; UA187.001.001.00019 (Box UA187 Shared 1)
- Academic Affairs Committee minutes, 1995 -- 2007; UA187.002; 2.4 Linear Feet
  This series contains files related to the Academic Affairs committee.
  This series is arranged chronologically.
  - MPH Academic Affairs [1 of 2], 1995 -- 1997; UA187.002.001.00020 (Box UA187 Shared 1)
  - MPH Academic Affairs [2 of 2], 1995 -- 1997; UA187.002.001.00021 (Box UA187 Shared 1)
  - Academic Affairs Committee, 1997 -- 1998; UA187.002.001.00022 (Box UA187 Shared 1)
  - Academic Affairs Committee, 1998 -- 1999; UA187.002.001.00023 (Box UA187 Shared 1)
  - Academic Affairs Committee, 1999 -- 2000; UA187.002.001.00024 (Box UA187 Shared 1)
  - Academic Affairs [1 of 2], 2000 -- 2001; UA187.002.002.00001 (Box UA187 Shared 2)
  - Academic Affairs [2 of 2], 2000 -- 2001; UA187.002.002.00002 (Box UA187 Shared 2)
  - Academic Affairs [1 of 2], 2001 -- 2002; UA187.002.002.00003 (Box UA187 Shared 2)
  - Academic Affairs [2 of 2], 2001 -- 2002; UA187.002.002.00004 (Box UA187 Shared 2)
  - Academic Affairs Committee GPPH [1 of 2], 2002 -- 2003; UA187.002.002.00005 (Box UA187 Shared 2)
  - Academic Affairs Committee GPPH [2 of 2], 2002 -- 2003; UA187.002.002.00006 (Box UA187 Shared 2)
  - Academic Affairs Committee Minutes GPPH [1 of 2], 2003 -- 2004; UA187.002.002.00007 (Box UA187 Shared 2)
  - Academic Affairs Committee Minutes GPPH [2 of 2], 2003 -- 2004; UA187.002.002.00008 (Box UA187 Shared 2)
  - Academic Affairs Committee Minutes GPPH [1 of 2], 2004 -- 2005; UA187.002.002.00009 (Box UA187 Shared 2)
  - Academic Affairs Committee Minutes GPPH [2 of 2], 2004 -- 2005; UA187.002.002.00010 (Box UA187 Shared 2)
  - Academic Affairs Committee Minutes GPPH, 2005 -- 2006; UA187.002.002.00011 (Box UA187 Shared 2)
  - Academic Affairs Committee Minutes GPPH [1 of 2], 2006 -- 2007; UA187.002.002.00012 (Box UA187 Shared 2)
  - Academic Affairs Committee Minutes GPPH [2 of 2], 2006 -- 2007; UA187.002.002.00013 (Box UA187 Shared 2)
- Accreditation Files, 1996 -- 2011; UA187.003; 2.4 Linear Feet
  This series contains records related to the acceditation process for the Professional Degree Programs.
  - MPH Accreditation Working Docs [1 of 2], 1996 -- 1997; UA187.003.002.00001 (Box UA187 Shared 2)
  - MPH Accreditation Working Docs [2 of 2], 1996 -- 1997; UA187.003.002.00002 (Box UA187 Shared 2)
  - Accreditation Subcommittee Minutes, 2001; UA187.003.002.00003 (Box UA187 Shared 2)
  - GPPH Criterion, 2001; UA187.003.002.00004 (Box UA187 Shared 2)
  - Accreditation Subcommittee Minutes, 2002; UA187.003.003.00001 (Box 3)
  - GPPH Preliminary Accreditation Self-Study, 2001 -- 2011; UA187.003.003.00002 (Box 3)
  - GPPH Preliminary Accreditation Self-Study Appendices, 2001 -- 2011; UA187.003.003.00003 (Box 3)
  - GPHH Accreditation Self-Study, 2002 -- 2003; UA187.003.003.00004 (Box 3)
  - GPPH Accreditation Self-Study Appendicies [1 of 2], 2002 -- 2003; UA187.003.003.00005 (Box 3)
  - GPPH Accreditation Self-Study Appendicies [2 of 2], 2002 -- 2003; UA187.003.003.00006 (Box 3)
  - Service and Research Survey 2001, UA187.003.003.00007 (Box 3)
  - Student Survey [1 of 2], 2001; UA187.003.003.00008 (Box 3)
  - Student Survey [2 of 2], 2001; UA187.003.003.00009 (Box 3)
  - Faculty Survey, 2001; UA187.003.003.00010 (Box 3)
  - Alumni Survey [1 of 2], 2001; UA187.003.003.00011 (Box 3)
  - Alumni Survey [2 of 2], 2001; UA187.003.003.00012 (Box 3)
  - GPPH Accreditation Faculty Review [1 of 2], 2002; UA187.003.003.00013 (Box 3)
  - GPPH Accreditation Faculty Review [2 of 2], 2002; UA187.003.003.00014 (Box 3)
- Grade Sheets, 1990 -- 2005; UA187.004; 2.4 Linear Feet
  This series contains grade sheets and is restricted.
  75 years from the date of creation.
  - MD - MPH, Grade Sheets, 1990; UA187.004.004.00001 (Box 4)
  - MD - MPH, Grade Sheets, 1991; UA187.004.004.00002 (Box 4)
  - CMPH, Grade Sheets, 1992; UA187.004.004.00003 (Box 4)
  - CMPH, Grade Sheets, 1993; UA187.004.004.00004 (Box 4)
  - CMPH, Grade Sheets, 1994; UA187.004.004.00005 (Box 4)
  - CMPH, Grade Sheets, 1995; UA187.004.004.00006 (Box 4)
  - CMPH, Grade Sheets, 1996; UA187.004.004.00007 (Box 4)
  - CMPH, Grade Sheets, 1997; UA187.004.004.00008 (Box 4)
  - CMPH, Grade Sheets, 1998; UA187.004.004.00009 (Box 4)
  - CMPH, Grade Sheets, 1999; UA187.004.004.00010 (Box 4)
  - CMPH, Grade Sheets, 2000; UA187.004.004.00011 (Box 4)
  - MD/MBA, Grading Sheets, 1999; UA187.004.004.00012 (Box 4)
  - MD/MBA Grade Sheets (Prior to establishment of OSP), 1994; UA187.004.004.00013 (Box 4)
  - Grade Reports, Spring, 1995; UA187.004.004.00014 (Box 4)
  - Grade Reports, Fall, 1994; UA187.004.004.00015 (Box 4)
  - Intersession I, January, 1995; UA187.004.004.00016 (Box 4)
  - Intersession II, (5/2-5/15), 1995; UA187.004.004.00017 (Box 4)
  - Grade Reports, Summer, 1995; UA187.004.004.00018 (Box 4)
  - Grade Reports, Fall, 1995; UA187.004.004.00019 (Box 4)
  - Health Communication Grades, 1994; UA187.004.004.00020 (Box 4)
  - Grade Reports, Spring, 1996; UA187.004.004.00021 (Box 4)
  - Intersession II, (05/02 - 05/15), 1996; UA187.004.004.00022 (Box 4)
  - SSI, (05/16 - 06/30), 1996; UA187.004.004.00023 (Box 4)
  - SSII, (07/01 - 08/31), 1996; UA187.004.004.00024 (Box 4)
  - Grade Reports, Fall, 1996; UA187.004.004.00025 (Box 4)
  - Summer I, 1997; UA187.004.004.00026 (Box 4)
  - Summer II, 1997; UA187.004.004.00027 (Box 4)
  - Intersession I, January, 1997; UA187.004.004.00028 (Box 4)
  - Intersession II, 1997; UA187.004.004.00029 (Box 4)
  - Spring, 1997; UA187.004.004.00030 (Box 4)
  - Fall, 1997; UA187.004.004.00031 (Box 4)
  - Spring, 1998; UA187.004.004.00032 (Box 4)
  - Summer I, 1998; UA187.004.004.00033 (Box 4)
  - Summer II, 1998; UA187.004.004.00034 (Box 4)
  - Fall, 1998; UA187.004.004.00035 (Box 4)
  - Spring, 1999; UA187.004.004.00036 (Box 4)
  - Summer I, 1999; UA187.004.004.00037 (Box 4)
  - Summer II, 1999; UA187.004.004.00038 (Box 4)
  - Grades, Fall, 1999; UA187.004.004.00039 (Box 4)
  - Grades, Spring, 2000; UA187.004.004.00040 (Box 4)
  - Grades, Summer, 2000; UA187.004.004.00041 (Box 4)
  - Grades, Fall, 2000; UA187.004.004.00042 (Box 4)
  - Grades, Spring, 2001; UA187.004.004.00043 (Box 4)
  - Grades, Summer, 2001; UA187.004.005.00001 (Box 5)
  - Grades, Fall, 2001; UA187.004.005.00002 (Box 5)
  - Grades, Spring [1 of 2], 2002; UA187.004.005.00003 (Box 5)
  - Grades, Spring [2 of 2], 2002; UA187.004.005.00004 (Box 5)
  - Summer I and II, 2002; UA187.004.005.00005 (Box 5)
  - Grades, Fall, 2002; UA187.004.005.00006 (Box 5)
  - Grades, Spring, 2003; UA187.004.005.00007 (Box 5)
  - Grades, Summer, 2003; UA187.004.005.00008 (Box 5)
  - Grades, Fall, 2003; UA187.004.005.00009 (Box 5)
  - Grades, Spring, 2004; UA187.004.005.00010 (Box 5)
  - Grades, Summer, 2004; UA187.004.005.00011 (Box 5)
  - Fall, 2004; UA187.004.005.00012 (Box 5)
  - Grades, Spring, 2005; UA187.004.005.00013 (Box 5)
  - Grades, Summer, 2005; UA187.004.005.00014 (Box 5)
- Capstone Project reports, UA187.005.000001; 1 Volumes
- 2016 accessions, 1990 -- 2008; UA187.005.000002; 16.8 Linear Feet 14 record cartons
  This series is arranged alphabetically.
  Records containing information related to student education, staff and faculty employment, and Board of Trustees records are closed for 75 years from the date of creation.
  This series contains student files for various Public Health and Professional Degree Programs, including MD/MPH Graduates and Withdrawals; MPH Graduates (all programs: MS/MPH, JD/MPH, BA/MPH); HCOM Graduates and Withdrawals; and Pain, Research Education and Policy Graduates and Withdrawals.
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  Transferred by Janice Gilkes, the Director of Enrollment Services in Public Health and Professional Degree Programs at Tufts University School of Medicine, accession UA-2017-001.
  - MPH and Combined MPH Graduates and Withdrawals: A-Cr, 1990 -- 2008; UA187.006.006; 1.2 Linear Feet 1 record carton (Box 6-11, Box 6)
    75 years from date of creation.
  - MPH and Combined MPH Graduates and Withdrawals: Cu-H, 1990 -- 2008; UA187.006.007; 1.2 Linear Feet 1 record carton (Box 6-11, Box 7)
  - MPH and Combined MPH Graduates and Withdrawals: Ho-Na, 1990 -- 2008; UA187.006.008; 1.2 Linear Feet 1 record carton (Box 6-11, Box 8)
  - MPH and Combined MPH Graduates and Withdrawals: Nd-Sc, 1990 -- 2008; UA187.006.009; 1.2 Linear Feet 1 record carton (Box 6-11, Box 9)
  - MPH and Combined MPH Graduates and Withdrawals: Se-Z, 1990 -- 2008; UA187.006.010; 1.2 Linear Feet 1 record carton (Box 6-11, Box 10)
  - CMPH and MD/MPH Graduates and Withdrawals: A-Fi, 1990 -- 2008; UA187.006.011; 1.2 Linear Feet 1 record carton (Box 6-11, Box 11)
  - CMPH and MD/MPH Graduates and Withdrawals: Fi-Li, 1990 -- 2008; UA187.006.012; 1.2 Linear Feet 1 record carton (Box 12-17, Box 12)
  - CMPH and MD/MPH Graduates and Withdrawals: Lu-Sa, 1990 -- 2008; UA187.006.013; 1.2 Linear Feet 1 record carton (Box 12-17, Box 13)
  - Graduates and Withdrawals: A-W, 1990 -- 2008; UA187.006.014; 1.2 Linear Feet 1 record carton (Box 12-17, Box 14)
  - MD/MBA Graduates and Withdrawals: A-P, 1990 -- 2008; UA187.006.015; 1.2 Linear Feet 1 record carton (Box 12-17, Box 15)
  - CMPH and MD/MPH Graduates and Withdrawals: S-Z, 1990 -- 2008; UA187.006.016; 1.2 Linear Feet 1 record carton (Box 12-17, Box 16)
  - HCOM Graduates and Withdrawals: A-Z, 1990 -- 2008; UA187.006.017; 1.2 Linear Feet 1 record carton (Box 12-17, Box 17)
  - Withdrawals, 1990 -- 2008; UA187.006.018; 1.2 Linear Feet 1 record carton (Box 18-19; 86-89, Box 18)
  - Withdrawals, 1990 -- 2008; UA187.006.019; 1.2 Linear Feet 1 record carton (Box 18-19; 86-89, Box 19)